<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" 
          "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY date "Sep 2004"> 
  <!ENTITY appversion "0.1.x"> 
  <!ENTITY app "<application>Terminal</application>"> 
]>

<article id="Terminal" lang="en">

  <!-- Header -->
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Terminal Emulator</title>

    <copyright>
      <year>2004</year> <holder>os-cillation e.K.</holder>
    </copyright>

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Benedikt</firstname> <surname>Meurer</surname>
        <affiliation>
          <address><email>benny@xfce.org</email></address>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <releaseinfo>
      This manual describes the &app; software, version &appversion;.
    </releaseinfo>

  </articleinfo>

  <para>&nbsp;</para>

  <sect1 id="intro">
    <title>Introduction to &app;</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>What is a terminal emulator?</title>

      <para>The UNIX operating system were originally designed as a text-only
      system, controlled by commands entered with a keybaord. This is known
      as a command-line interface (CLI). The X Window System, Xfce and other
      projects have since added a graphical user interface to UNIX, thats
      what you are actually using now. But the addition of a graphical user
      interface doesn't mean, that the CLI is dead. The CLI is still around,
      and is frequently the easiest, fastest and most powerful way to perform
      a certain task. In fact, power users would be lost without the CLI.</para>

      <para>&app; is what is known as an X terminal emulator, often referred
      to as terminal or shell. It provides an equivalent to the old fashioned
      text screen on your desktop, but on which can easily share the screen
      with other graphical applications. Windows users may already be familar
      with the MS-DOS Prompt utility, which has the analogous function of
      offering a DOS command-line under Windows, though one should note, that
      the UNIX CLI offer far more power and ease of use than does DOS.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>What makes &app; special?</title>

      <para>&app;'s advanced features include a simple configuration interface, the
      ability to use multiple tabs with terminals within a single window, the possibility
      to have a pseudo-transparent terminal background and a compact mode, that helps
      you to save space on your desktop.</para>

      <para>The following key features are available:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>Multiple tabs per window</listitem>
        <listitem>Nearly every aspect of the terminal itself is configurable</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="getting-started">
    <title>Getting started</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>Starting &app;</title>

      <para>The easiest way to start &app; is to use the applications menu of your desktop -
      for Xfce, point your mouse cursor to the desktop, press the right mouse button
      and choose <application>Terminal</application> from the
      <application>System</application> menu.</para>

      <para>You can also start &app; from a command line or from the <application>Application
      launcher</application>. Just hit <emphasis>ALT+F2</emphasis>, type
      <emphasis>Terminal</emphasis> and press the button
      <emphasis role="bold">Run</emphasis>.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>When you first start &app;</title>

      <para>When you start &app; for the first time, the application opens a terminal window
      with using default settings.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/terminal-first-time.png" format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Example of a default terminal window</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>The terminal window displays a command prompt where you can type UNIX
      commands. The command prompt may vary depending on the configuration of
      your shell. The cursor is positioned at the command prompt. When you type a
      UNIX command and press <emphasis role="bold">Return</emphasis>, the computer
      executes the command. By default, &app; will use the login shell of the user
      who starts the application.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Working with multiple terminals</title>

      <para>&app; provides a tab feature that enables you to open several terminal
      within a single window. Each terminal is opened in a separate tab. Click on the
      appropriate tab to display the terminal in the window. Each tabbed terminal in
      a window is separate subprocess, so you can use each terminal for a different
      task.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/terminal-multiple-tabs.png" format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Example of a terminal window with tabs</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="copyright">
    <title>About &app;</title>

    <para>&app; was written by Benedikt Meurer (<email>benny@xfce.org</email>). Visit the
    <ulink url="http://www.os-cillation.com/" type="http">os-cillation website</ulink>
    for more information.</para>

    <para>To report a bug or make a suggestion regarding this application or this
    manual, use the bug tracking system at <ulink
    url="http://bugs.os-cillation.de/">http://bugs.os-cillation.de/</ulink>. If you
    have questions about the use or installation of this software, please ask on the
    <ulink url="http://www.os-cillation.de/cgi-bin/yabb/YaBB.cgi#terminal_cat">os-cillation
    forum</ulink>
    or join the channel <emphasis role="bold">#xfce</emphasis> on <emphasis
    role="bold">irc.freenode.net</emphasis> and ask for help.</para>

    <para>This software is distributed under the terms of the GNU General Public License
    as published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2 of the License, or
    (at your option) any later version.</para>

    <para>You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License 
    along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software 
    Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place - Suite 330, Boston, MA 02111-1307, 
    USA.</para>

  </sect1>

</article>

<!--
	vim:set ts=2 sw=2 et ai:
-->
