<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" 
          "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY date "Oct 2004"> 
  <!ENTITY appversion "0.1.10"> 
  <!ENTITY app "<application>Terminal</application>"> 
]>

<article id="index" lang="en">

  <!-- Header -->
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Terminal Emulator</title>

    <copyright>
      <year>2003</year>
      <year>2004</year>
      <holder>os-cillation</holder>
    </copyright>

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Benedikt</firstname>
        <surname>Meurer</surname>
        <affiliation>
          <address><email>benny@xfce.org</email></address>
          <orgname>os-cillation</orgname>
          <orgdiv>System development</orgdiv>
          <jobtitle>Software developer</jobtitle>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <releaseinfo>
      This manual describes the &app; software, version &appversion;.
    </releaseinfo>

  </articleinfo>

  <para>&nbsp;</para>

  <sect1 id="intro">
    <title>Introduction to &app;</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>What is a terminal emulator?</title>

      <para>The UNIX operating system were originally designed as a text-only
      system, controlled by commands entered with a keyboard. This is known
      as a command-line interface (CLI). The X Window System, Xfce and other
      projects have since added a graphical user interface to UNIX, thats
      what you are actually using now. But the addition of a graphical user
      interface doesn't mean, that the CLI is dead. The CLI is still around,
      and is frequently the easiest, fastest and most powerful way to perform
      a certain task. In fact, power users would be lost without the CLI.</para>

      <para>&app; is what is known as an X terminal emulator, often referred
      to as terminal or shell. It provides an equivalent to the old fashioned
      text screen on your desktop, but on which can easily share the screen
      with other graphical applications. Windows users may already be familar
      with the MS-DOS Prompt utility, which has the analogous function of
      offering a DOS command-line under Windows, though one should note, that
      the UNIX CLI offer far more power and ease of use than does DOS.</para>

      <para>&app; emulates the <application>xterm</application> application
      developed by the X Consortium. In turn, the <application>xterm</application>
      application emulates the DEC VT102 terminal and also supports the DEC VT220
      escape sequences. An escape sequence is a series of characters that start
      with the <keycap>Esc</keycap> character. &app; accepts all of the escape
      sequences that the VT102 and VT220 terminals use for functions such as to
      position the cursor and to clear the screen.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>What makes &app; special?</title>

      <para>&app;'s advanced features include a simple configuration interface, the
      ability to use multiple tabs with terminals within a single window, the possibility
      to have a pseudo-transparent terminal background and a compact mode, where both the
      menubar and the window decorations are hidden, that helps you to save space on your
      desktop.</para>

      <para>The following key features are available:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          Supports multiple tabs per window
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          Includes support for customizable toolbars, which can be changed using an integrated graphical toolbar editor
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          Nearly every aspect of the terminal itself is configurable through the <guilabel>Terminal Preferences</guilabel> dialog
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          Integrates well with the <ulink url="http://xfce.org/">Xfce desktop environment</ulink>, but also with every other Linux desktop
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          Standard compliance (see the <ulink url="http://freedesktop.org/">freedesktop.org</ulink> website)
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <ulink url="http://dbus.freedesktop.org/">D-BUS</ulink> based terminal service facility to minimize the number of processes in the system
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          High degree of maintainability by making best use of <ulink url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/">Gtk+</ulink>
          and <ulink url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gobject/">GObject</ulink>.
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Besides these key features, &app; supports all features you would expect from a modern
      terminal emulator.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="getting-started">
    <title>Getting started</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>Starting &app;</title>

      <para>The easiest way to start &app; is to use the applications menu of your desktop -
      for Xfce, point your mouse cursor to the desktop, press the right mouse button
      and choose <menuchoice><guimenu>System</guimenu><guimenuitem>Terminal</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>

      <para>You can also start &app; from a command line or from the <guilabel>Application
      launcher</guilabel>. Just hit <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F2</keycap></keycombo>, type
      <emphasis>Terminal</emphasis> and press the button
      <guilabel>Run</guilabel>.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>When you first start &app;</title>

      <para>When you start &app; for the first time, the application opens a terminal window
      with default settings.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/terminal-first-time.png" format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Example of a default terminal window</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>The terminal window displays a command prompt where you can type UNIX
      commands. The command prompt may vary depending on the configuration of
      your shell. The cursor is positioned at the command prompt. When you type a
      UNIX command and press <emphasis role="bold">Return</emphasis>, the computer
      executes the command. By default, &app; will use the login shell of the user
      who starts the application.</para>

      <para>&app; also sets the following environment variables:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><varname>TERM</varname></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Set to <literal>xterm</literal> or <literal>xterm-color</literal>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><varname>COLORTERM</varname></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Set to <literal>Terminal</literal> by default.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><varname>DISPLAY</varname></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Set to the X11 display of the terminal by default.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><varname>WINDOWID</varname></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Set to the X11 window identifier of the terminal by default.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Working with multiple terminals</title>

      <para>&app; provides a tab feature that enables you to open several terminal
      within a single window. Each terminal is opened in a separate tab. Click on the
      appropriate tab to display the terminal in the window. Each tabbed terminal in
      a window is separate subprocess, so you can use each terminal for a different
      task.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/terminal-multiple-tabs.png" format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Example of a terminal window with tabs</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>See <xref linkend="usage" /> for information about how to open a new tabbed
      terminal.</para>
    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="usage">
    <title>Usage</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>To open and close terminals</title>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>To open a new terminal window:</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Open
            Terminal</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
            <para>The new terminal inherits the working directory from its parent
            terminal.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>To close a terminal window:</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Close
            Window</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
            <para>This action closes the terminal and terminates any subprocesses that
            you opened from the terminal. If you close the last terminal window, the
            &app; application exits.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>To add a new tabbed terminal to a window:</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Open
            Tab</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>To modify a terminal window</title>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>To hide the menubar:</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>View</guimenu><guimenuitem>Show Menubar</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>To show a hidden menubar:</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Right-click the terminal window and choose <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Show Menubar</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
            from the popup menu.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>To show or hide the toolbars:</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>View</guimenu><guimenuitem>Show Toolbars</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>To customize the toolbars:</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Be sure to show the toolbars first; then choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Toolbars</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>To show or hide the window decorations:</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>View</guimenu><guimenuitem>Show Window Borders</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>To change the appearance of the terminal window:</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>See <xref linkend="preferences" /> for information about the options that you choose in
            the <guilabel>Terminal Preferences</guilabel> dialog to change the appearance and behaviour
            of the terminal windows. For example, you can change the background color or the location of
            the scrollbar.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>To work with the contents of terminal windows</title>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>To scroll through previous commands and output:</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Perform one of the following actions:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Use the scrollbar, which is usually displayed on the right side
                of each terminal window.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Press the <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Page Up</keycap></keycombo>,
                <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Page Down</keycap></keycombo>,
                <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Home</keycap></keycombo>, or
                <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>End</keycap></keycombo> keys.</para>
              </listitem> 
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>The number of lines that you can scroll back in the terminal window is
            determined by the <guilabel>Scrollback</guilabel> setting in the <guilabel>General</guilabel>
            section of the <guilabel>Terminal Preferences</guilabel> dialog.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>To select and copy text:</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>You can select text in any of the following ways:</para>
            <itemizedlist> 
              <listitem> 
                <para>To select a character at a time, click on the first character that you want to
                select and drag the mouse to the last character that you want to select.</para>
              </listitem> 
              <listitem> 
                <para>To select a word at a time, double-click on the first word that you want to
                select and drag the mouse to the last word that you want to select.</para>
              </listitem> 
              <listitem> 
                <para>To select a line at a time, triple-click on the first line that you want to
                select and drag the mouse to the last line that you want to select.</para>
              </listitem> 
            </itemizedlist> 
            <para>These actions select all text between the first and last items. For all text selections,
            &app; copies the selected text into the clipboard when you release the mouse button. To
            explicitly copy the selected text, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Copy</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
          </listitem> 
        </varlistentry> 
        <varlistentry> 
          <term>To paste text into a terminal:</term> 
          <listitem> 
            <para>If you previously copied text to the clipboard, you can paste the text into a
            terminal by performing one of the following actions:</para>
            <itemizedlist> 
              <listitem> 
                <para>To paste text that you copied by selection only, middle-click at the
                command prompt. If you do not have a middle mouse button, refer to the X
                Server documentation for information about how to emulate the middle mouse button.</para>
              </listitem> 
              <listitem> 
                <para>To paste text that you explicitly copied, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
                <guimenuitem>Paste</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
              </listitem> 
            </itemizedlist> 
          </listitem> 
        </varlistentry> 
        <varlistentry> 
          <term>To drag a file name into a terminal window:</term> 
          <listitem> 
            <para>You can drag a file name to a terminal from another application such as a file manager or
            a web browser. The terminal displays the path and the full name of the URI.</para>
          </listitem> 
        </varlistentry> 
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="set-title">
      <title>To change the terminal title</title>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/terminal-set-title.png" format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Set title dialog</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>To change the title of the currently displayed terminal, perform the following
      three steps:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Terminal</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Set Title</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Type the new title in the <guilabel>Title</guilabel> text box. &app; applies
          the change immediately.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click the button <guilabel>Close</guilabel> or press the <keycap>Return</keycap>
          key to close the <guilabel>Set Title</guilabel> dialog.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>To reset the terminal title to its default behaviour, perform the same three steps
      as described above, but enter an empty title.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>To recover your terminal</title>

      <para>This section provides some advice if you have problems with terminals.</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>To reset the state of the terminal:</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Terminal</guimenu><guimenuitem>Reset</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>To reset the terminal and clear the terminal screen:</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Terminal</guimenu><guimenuitem>Reset and Clear</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="toolbars">
      <title>To customize the toolbars</title>

      <para>As already mentioned, &app; includes support for customizable toolbars. The toolbars
      are disabled by default, you will have to explicitly enabed it. Choose
      <menuchoice><guimenu>View</guimenu><guimenuitem>Show Toolbars</guimenuitem></menuchoice> from
      the menubar to display the toolbars in the current window. If you want to permanently use
      the toolbars, see <xref linkend="preferences-general" />.</para>

      <para>Once the toolbars are shown choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Toolbars</guimenuitem></menuchoice> from the menubar. This opens the
      <guilabel>Toolbar Editor</guilabel> window, which allows you to customize the
      toolbars in the current terminal window.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/terminal-toolbars.png" format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Customizing the toolbars</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>Just drag an item from the <guilabel>Toolbar Editor</guilabel> window and drop
      it on a toolbar to add that item to the specific toolbar or drag an item from a toolbar
      to the <guilabel>Toolbar Editor</guilabel> to remove it from the toolbar. You can add
      additional toolbars by clicking the button <guibutton>Add a new toolbar</guibutton>
      and remove toolbars by right-clicking the toolbar and selecting
      <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Remove Toolbar</guimenuitem></menuchoice> from the context
      menu. You can also choose a different style for a toolbar from the context menu.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="luit">
      <title>To switch between different encodings</title>

      <para>&app; itself does not (yet) include builtin support for switching encodings
      on the fly in a terminal session. But since &app; implements an UTF-8 mode, you
      can use the <ulink url="http://www.pps.jussieu.fr/~jch/software/luit/">Luit
      application</ulink> to switch between different character encodings within a terminal
      session.</para>
    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="preferences">
    <title>Preferences</title>

    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/terminal-edit-preferences.png" format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>

        <textobject>
          <phrase>Preferences</phrase>
        </textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <para>To configure &app;, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice> or right-click the terminal area of the window and choose
    <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. This will bring up the <guilabel>Terminal
    Preferences</guilabel> dialog, which allows you to adjust &app;'s behaviour to your needs.</para>

    <sect2 id="preferences-general">
      <title>General</title>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/terminal-preferences-general.png" format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>General preferences</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Initial title</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Use this text box to specify the initial title of terminals.
            New terminals will have the initial title.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Dynamically-set title</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Use this drop-down list to specify how to handle dynamically-set
            titles, that is, terminal titles set by the commands that run in the
            terminal.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Run command as login shell</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select this option to force the command that currently runs inside
            the terminal to run as a login shell. The setting has no effect if you
            have selected <guilabel>Run a custom command instead of my shell</guilabel>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Update utmp/wtmp records when command is launched</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select this option to insert a new entry in the utmp and wtmp records
            when a new terminal is opened.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Scrollbar is</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Use this drop-down list to specify the position of the scrollbar on
            the terminal window.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Scrollback</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Use this spin box to specify the number of lines that you can scroll
            back using the scrollbar or the mouse wheel. For example, if you specify
            1000 you can scroll back the last 1000 lines displayed in the terminal.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Scroll on output</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select this option to enable you to scroll the output on the terminal
            while the terminal continues to display more output from a command.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Scroll on keystroke</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select this option to enable you to press any key on the keyboard to
            scroll down the terminal window to the command prompt. This action only
            applies if you scrolled up the terminal window and you want to return
            to the command prompt.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Show menubar by default</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select this option to show the menubar on new terminal windows by default.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Terminal bell</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select this option to enable the audible terminal bell.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Show toolbars by default</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select this option to show toolbars on new terminal windows by default.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Cursor blinks</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select this option to display a cursor that blinks.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Show borders by default</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select this option to show window decorations on new terminal windows by default.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Appearance</title>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/terminal-preferences-appearance.png" format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Appearance preferences</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Font</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click on this button to select a font type and font size for the terminal.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Colors</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click on the <guilabel>Text color</guilabel> button to choose the color
            &app; uses to draw normal text - an application running inside the terminal can
            also request a different color choosen from the palette below to draw text.</para>

            <para>Click on the <guilabel>Background color</guilabel> button to choose the
            default background for terminal windows. This color is also used in background
            tinting when <guilabel>Transparent background</guilabel> or <guilabel>Background
            image</guilabel> is selected below.</para>

            <para>The terminal provides the application running inside with a palette of
            16 colors. You can customize this colors using the 16 color buttons.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Background</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select a background for the terminal window. The options are as follows:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <guilabel>None (use solid color)</guilabel>
                <para>Select this option to use the background color that is specified
                in the <guilabel>Colors</guilabel> section as the background color for
                the terminal.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <guilabel>Background image</guilabel>
                <para>Select this option to use an image file as the background for the
                terminal. Use the <guilabel>Image file</guilabel> entry box to
                specify the location and name of the image file. Alternatively, click on
                the button besides the entry box to search for and select the image
                file.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <guilabel>Transparent background</guilabel>
                <para>Select this option to use a transparent background for the terminal.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>If you have selected <guilabel>Background image</guilabel> or <guilabel>Transparent
            background</guilabel>, you can use the slider <guilabel>Shade transparent or image
            background</guilabel> to shade or dim the background of the terminal.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Shortcuts</title>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/terminal-preferences-shortcuts.png" format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Shortcut preferences</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Disable menu shortcut key (F10 by default)</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select this option to disable the shortcut key that is defined to
            enable you to access the &app; menus. The default shortcut key to access
            the menus is <keycap>F10</keycap>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Shortcut keys</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>The <guilabel>Shortcut keys</guilabel> section of the dialog lists the
            shortcut keys that are defined for each menu item. The shortcut keys enable
            you to use the keyboard to choose a menu item rather than use the mouse. A
            shortcut key can be any non-modifier key or any combination of a non-modifier
            key and several modifier keys, where modifier keys are <keycap>Alt</keycap>,
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> and the like.</para>

            <screenshot>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/terminal-compose-shortcut.png" format="PNG" />
                </imageobject>
                
                <textobject>
                  <phrase>Compose shortcut</phrase>
                </textobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
            
            <para>To change a shortcut key for a menu item, double click the item in the list
            and press the key combination you want to set. To disable a shortcut for a specific
            menu item, double click the menu item in the list and click the button
            <guilabel>Clear</guilabel>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Advanced</title>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/terminal-preferences-advanced.png" format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Advanced preferences</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Backspace key generates</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Use the drop-down list to select the function that you want the
            <keycap>Backspace</keycap> key to perform.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Delete key generates</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Use the drop-down list to select the function that you want the
            <keycap>Delete</keycap> key to perform.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>$TERM setting</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>This specifies the value the $TERM environment variable is set to, when a
            new terminal tab or terminal window is opened. The default should be ok for most
            systems. If you have problems with colors in some applications, try xterm-color here.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Reset compatibility options to defaults</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click this button to reset the options on the <guilabel>Compatibility</guilabel>
            tabbed section to its defaults settings.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Double click</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Use this text box to specify characters or groups of characters that &app;
            considers to be words when you select text by word.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="faq">
    <title>Frequently asked questions</title>

    <para>The intent of this section is to collect the quite numerous frequently asked
    question that relate to working with &app;, or even terminal emulators in general. If
    you know of a question thats missing from this page, please <ulink
    url="http://bugs.os-cillation.de/enter_bug.cgi?product=Terminal&amp;component=docs">file a request</ulink>.</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>&app; complains about <literal>Unable to start terminal server: Unable to connect
        to D-BUS message daemon</literal>, what can I do?</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>&app; tries to reduce the number of running instances by establishing a D-BUS service
          that handles all terminal windows. The message above tells you that &app; wasn't able to
          connect to the D-BUS session message daemon and register a service. This is just a warning,
          you can use the terminal without the D-BUS service feature as well.</para>

          <para>To start the D-BUS session message daemon when you login to your X session, either
          modify your xinitrc file and change the line <literal>xfce4-session</literal> to
          <literal>dbus-launch xfce4-session</literal> or use <literal>dbus-launch startxfce4</literal>
          to start Xfce instead. If you don't use Xfce, please look at the documentation of your
          desktop environment on how to enable the D-BUS session daemon.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><keycap>Home</keycap> and <keycap>End</keycap> keys don't work in &app;, what's wrong?</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>This problem is actually a bug in <ulink url="http://developer.gnome.org/arch/gnome/widgets/vte.html">vte</ulink>,
          the terminal widget used by &app;. A patch for vte that fixes the problem is available <ulink
          url="http://lunar-linux.org/lunar/patches/vte-0.11.11-termcap.patch">here</ulink> (this patch was created
          with version 0.11.11 of vte, it may not work with other versions). Thanks to Auke Kok for this patch.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>How to customize the menus in &app;?</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>You can customize the main menubar and the right-click popup menu by editing the file
          <filename>Terminal/Terminal.ui</filename>. Create a copy of this file before you actually
          start editing it. For example, say you installed Terminal in <filename>/usr/local</filename>,
          then you would perform the following steps:</para>

<screen>$ mkdir -p ~/.local/share/Terminal
$ cd ~/.local/share/Terminal
$ cp /usr/local/share/Terminal/Terminal.ui .</screen>

          <para>Now you can safely edit the file <filename>~/.local/share/Terminal/Terminal.ui</filename>
          to customize the menus. See the <ulink
          url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkUIManager.html">GtkUIManager</ulink> documentation
          for details on the file format. The changes will only be visible in new terminal windows.</para>

          <para>If you choose to customize your menus this way, you'll have to take care to sync
          your customized <filename>Terminal.ui</filename> file when you upgrade to a newer &app;
          release to keep up with user interface changes and additions.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="support">
    <title>Support</title>

    <para>To report a bug or make a suggestion regarding this application or this
    manual, use the bug tracking system at <ulink
    url="http://bugs.os-cillation.de/enter_bug.cgi?product=Terminal">http://bugs.os-cillation.de/</ulink>.
    Remember, that useful bug reports are ones that get bugs fixed, and so a useful bug report
    has two qualities:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Reproducible.</emphasis> If the developer cannot see the bug himself
        to prove that it exists, he will most probably not be able to fix it at all. Every detail you
        can provide helps.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Specific.</emphasis> The quicker the developer can isolate the problem
        to a specific area, the more likely he will expediently fix it.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>In case you want to request a new feature, please make clear why you consider it a worth
    addition for the application. It is more likely, that a new feature gets added if you provide
    good arguments for the feature. It will increase the chance of addition even more, if you
    provide a patch that implements the requested feature, but make sure that you read the file
    <ulink url="https://www.os-cillation.de:8080/websvn/filedetails.php?repname=terminal&amp;path=%2Ftrunk%2FHACKING">HACKING</ulink>
    - especially the section labeled <emphasis>Coding Style</emphasis> - before you start hacking up the source.</para>

    <para>Else, if you have questions about the use or installation of this software, please ask on the
    <ulink url="http://www.os-cillation.de/cgi-bin/yabb/YaBB.cgi#terminal_cat">os-cillation
    forum</ulink> or point your IRC client to <emphasis role="bold">irc.freenode.net</emphasis>,
    join the channel <emphasis role="bold">#xfce</emphasis> and ask for help.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="copyright">
    <title>About &app;</title>

    <para>&app; was written by Benedikt Meurer (<email>benny@xfce.org</email>). Visit the
    <ulink url="http://www.os-cillation.com/" type="http">os-cillation website</ulink>
    for more information.</para>

    <para>This software is distributed under the terms of the GNU General Public License
    as published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2 of the License, or
    (at your option) any later version.</para>

    <para>You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License 
    along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software 
    Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place - Suite 330, Boston, MA 02111-1307, 
    USA.</para>

  </sect1>

</article>

<!--
	vim:set ts=2 sw=2 et ai:
-->
